Khizer Naeem

✓ khizernaeem@gmail.com https://github.com/kxr in linkedin.com/in/khizern

PROFILE

Seasoned Cloud Architect and Systems Engineer, accumulating over 13 years of industry experience. Specialized in OpenShift, Core OS, Red Hat Enterprise Linux, Kubernetes, Devops and Cloud-Native technologies. Open Source contributor and enthusiast.

Possess broad competence in leading complex cloud adoption and transformation initiatives with a distinct ability to drive the engagements from technical level up to the executive level.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Broad level of expertise in OpenShift, Kubernetes and Kube-Native technologies.
- Adept in architecting micro-services based high performance and fault tolerant applications.
- Expert in Enterprise Linux and relevant Open Source technologies.
- Well versed with cloud computing and major cloud providers including AWS.
- Proficient in scripting, tooling and automation.
- Well familiar with a broad spectrum of Devops tools and technologies.
- Good understanding of modern development frameworks.
- Enthusiastic about logging, monitoring and performance testing.
- Proven record of excellent troubleshooting, analytical and problem solving skills.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Principal Technical Account Manager - OpenShift Senior Technical Account Manager - OpenShift Technical Account Manager - Platform

Apr 2022 - Present Mar 2020 - Apr 2022 May 2018 - Mar 2020



💄 Red Hat – Dubai

- Ensuring customer success and best possible support experience through an attentive, direct and tailored relationship with strategic enterprise customers, effectively becoming their trusted adviser.
- Engaging with customer leadership and C-level executives to align on strategic objectives and ensuring Red Hat portfolio delivers maximum possible value.
- Advocating for customer's needs and business requirements by establishing an effective feedback loop between customers and Red Hat's engineering and product management teams.
- Performing technical reviews and sharing knowledge to proactively identify and prevent issues and providing best-practice advice for long-term supportability.
- Designing and delivering tailor made workshops and webinars aimed at building and improving particular skill sets and filling knowledge gaps within the customer's organization.
- Engaging with Red Hat's field teams, customers, and partners to ensure a positive cloud technology experience and a successful outcome, targeting long-term and sustainable enterprise success.
- Handling critical and high-stake escalations by leading from the front. Facilitating issue resolution by becoming the focal person and converging all the required resources.
- Assisting management in hiring new talent and later on-boarding and mentoring new members joining the team.

Hamdan Bin Mohammed Smart University – Dubai

HBMSU is a research-based online University pioneering smart education in UAE. It offers a modern learning experience with the use of technologies in the form of mobile learning, discussion blogs, online classrooms, educational gaming and social networking.

- Responsible for deployment, administration and maintenance of Linux (Red Hat, Oracle Linux, Ubuntu) based infrastructure that run the University's core online applications and services, running in various highly available, load balanced and scale-able clusters.
- Took and led the AWS cloud transformation initiative. Worked with development and operations teams to bring them on board with the cloud transformation. Created various tools to remove blockers eventually leading to a successful migration to AWS.
- Designed and implemented Nagios/Icinga2 based host, services and application monitoring. Developed custom monitoring scripts to monitor various aspects of the infrastructure including application performance, cluster statistics and backup operations.
- Took the initiative to create a performance testing framework. Ran and analyzed regular stress tests on the core business applications which in turn identified various bottle necks, improved user experience and application performance under peak load times.
- Worked closely with the development team to improve the architectural design of the applications and their integrations.
- Received several performance and initiative rewards from the Assistant Chancellor, recognizing outstanding performance, initiatives and innovations.

Systems Engineer Dec 2010 – May 2014

INTEGRA Integra Technologies - Sharjah

Integra Technologies is a Red Hat Advanced Partner and Amazon Advanced Consulting Partner, focused on providing Amazon Web Services (AWS) and Linux based business solutions to enterprises in the Dubai, UAE and the wider Middle East.

- Responsible for designing, installing, securing and maintaining more than 50 Linux based mission critical servers and infrastructures for numerous clients spread across the Middle East.
- Providing technical consultation to the enterprise customers for a broad range of IT operations, including minimizing down times during software and hardware upgrades, designing backups and disaster recovery strategies, ensuring system security and stability etc.
- Researching, testing and often bench-marking available open source and other solutions to assess whether they are ready to meet the demands of our enterprise customers.
- Responding to support calls from clients and alerts from the monitoring system. Debug and troubleshoot production issues on live environments, provide remote and on-site support.

Assistant System Administrator

lan 2010 - Nov 2010



- Administration of Linux based corporate Email, Web, DNS, Proxy, FTP servers which serve more than 2000 users of Hashoo Group.
- Administration of Windows Server based IIS web servers, hosting ASP.NET based corporate websites.
- Monitoring email, web and network traffic, ensuring smooth operation and up time.
- Providing Enterprise level Server Setup and maintenance support to Hashoo group of companies which include some of the largest 5 star hotel chains across Pakistan.

Network Support Engineer

Apr 2009 - Dec 2009

NAVAted Micronet Broadband / Nayatel - Islamabad

- Part of the team managing Linux and Windows based Email, DNS, Proxy, FTP and many other servers which serve more than 15000 customers of Micronet/Nayatel (ISP).
- Managing C-panel/WHM which provide web hosting services to more than 500 live domains.
- Assisting system administrators and providing support to corporate and SLA customers.

TRAINING AND CERTIFICATIONS	
AWS Certified Solutions Architect – Professional (#2353)	Jul 2016
AWS Certified Solutions Architect – Associate (#9635)	Aug 2015
Commvault Implementation and Maintenance	Dec 2014
Commvault Core Fundamentals	Dec 2014
Oracle VM Administration	Aug 2014
Red Hat Certified Engineer (111-112-272)	Oct 2011
Red Hat Certified System Administrator (111-112-272)	Jun 2011
EDUCATION	
MS in Networking and Systems Administration	2017 – 2020
Rochester Institute of Technology, New York, USA	
BS in Electronic Engineering (Major in Computer Systems)	2004 - 2008
International Islamic University, Islamabad, Pakistan	
VISA STATUS	

• Australia: Permanent Resident (SC 189)